Guide to the Rigsbee Family Deeds records, 1858-1902 UA.01.17.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rigsbee Family Deeds records
1858-1902
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rigsbee, Atlas Munroe, 1841-1903
Angier, Malbourne Addison, 1820-1900
Rigsbee, Thomas Jefferson, 1846-1917
UA.01.17.0001
.5 Linear Feet
Duke University's West Campus sits on land that was once part of the Rigsbee family's 600 acre farm. Along with the Angier, Blackwell, Carlton, Ferrell, Mangum, Maynor, Strayhorn, and Styron families, the Rigsbees bought and sold properties that have become much of the city of Durham. Records include twenty-six original documents, deeds, and an easement reflecting the legal transactions for land and properties bought and sold in Durham and Orange Counties.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Duke University's West Campus sits on land that was once part of the Rigsbee family's 600 acre farm. Along with the Angier, Blackwell, Carlton, Ferrell, Mangum, Maynor, Strayhorn, and Styron families, the Rigsbee's bought and sold properties that have become much of the city of Durham. The family deeds are also a reflection of the transactions which shaped areas of downtown to accommodate Erwin Mills, the Ninth Street area, general stores, textile and saw mills, and other businesses. As Mary Whitworth Leigh Rigsbee, Rowena Margaret Brassfield Rigsbee, Nancy H. Brassfield Rigsbee, and other wives are included in the deeds, the women were involved in managing land assets.
Jesse Rigsbee, a Revolutionary War veteran, and one of the two Jesse Rigsbee's in the county, established his family in eastern Orange County. In 1790, the federal census records William Rigsby of Duplin County as a holder of two enslaved people. By 1840 there were 25 Rigsbee families living in North Carolina. The 1850 U.S. Federal Census Slave Schedules, document other Rigsbee family members as holding enslaved people, as did James Blackwell, M. L. Carlton, Simeon Ferrell, William Mangum, John Strayhorn, Wallace Styron.
From the late 1790s to the mid-1910s, the Rigsbee family farm produced tobacco, corn and sweet potatoes. Jesse Rigsbee and Mary Vickers Rigsbee's son, Atlas Munroe Rigsbee lived on the northwest corner of what is now East Chapel Hill Street, and Rigsbee Avenue. A. M. Rigsbee's farm included Mangum Street and Cleveland-Holloway. His brother, Thomas Jefferson Rigsbee, purchased large tracts west of Durham.
The small cemetery, near Duke's Wallace Wade Stadium is the only remaining Rigsbee family farm property. The cemetery is described as: "a three foot high stone wall and steel gate encloses approximately 12 graves set around two small pine trees." A Duke Chronicle reporter wrote that shortly before Thomas J. Rigsbee Jr. became the last person laid to rest in the graveyard in 1924, he sat on the low cemetery wall and James B. Duke told Rigsbee his plans to build a university. In 1925, Murray Jones then purchased several hundred acres of forest and farmland from Rigsbee's widow on James Duke's behalf, and the Rigsbee family retained ownership of the graveyard. While the Rigsbee's farm made up the bulk of the original West Campus, it was only a portion of the land purchased for the Dukes by Jones for the future home of Trinity College, later renamed Duke University.
Sources, accessed 11/24/2020: https://www.oldwestdurham.org/history/; https://www.opendurham.org/buildings/thomas-j-rigsbee-farm-duke-university-west-campus; https://www.dukechronicle.com/article/tombstones-blue-zone; https://www.ancestry.com/name-origin?surname=rigsbee; https://www.ancestrylibrary.com/imageviewer/collections/5058/images/4440913_00368?pId=16681; http://hindskw.com/KennethHinds/5919.html; https://www.genealogy.com/forum/surnames/topics/rigsby/840/
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Rigsbee Family Deeds records were received by the Duke University Archives as a gift in 2018.
Related Materials
Duke Real Estate Office records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Collection Overview
Records include twenty-six original documents, deeds, and an easement reflecting the legal transactions for land and properties bought and sold in Durham and Orange Counties. The scope and content for each item includes, if known, location of each deed's registration in the official deed book by name/number, and page number, its registration date, and an abbreviated description of the property taken from the original document.
Real estate management -- North Carolina; Real property -- North Carolina; Durham County (N.C.) -- History; Rigsbee, Mary Whitworth Leigh, 1854–1908; Rigsbee, Henry Jackson, 1832-1861; Strayhorn, Chaney, 1821–1892; Strayhorn, John, 1812–1891; Strayhorn, Parthenia, 1808–1888; Durham, Catherine Borland Strayhorn, 1816–1883; Rigsbee, Rowena Margaret Brassfield, 1842–1921; Angier, Mary Jane Pearson, 1820-1906; Mangum, William J., 1824–1905; Carlton, Marcus L., 1850-1911; Carlton, Bettie Vaughan Groom, 1858–1922; Cheek, James Alvis, 1842-1911; Cheek, Rosanna Faucett, 1854-1946; Parrish, Edward James, 1846-1920; Parrish, Rosa Bryan, 1852-1927; Maynor, William, 1834–1892; Rigsbee, Nancy H. Brassfield, 1848–1880; Styron, Wallace Kenneth, 1835–1914; Styron, Sarah J. "Sallie" Rogers, 1846-1917; Rigsbee, John Vernon, 1848-1912; Blackwell, James Washington, 1855–1932; Duke University -- History; Duke University. West Campus
- E.W. Pickett sold to H.J. Rigsbee, 1858 September 18 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Registered in deed book 4, on page 42, on September 21, 1885: on the waters of New Hope adjoining the lands of Page ..., David Vickers, William Protors and others, containing twelve and a half acres more or less.
- Elizabeth Strayhorn, Parthenia Strayhorn, Catherine Strayhorn, John Strayhorn and, Chaney Strayhorn sold to Henry J. Rigsbee, 1860 January 20 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 3, page 189-190, in 1885: on the waters of Ellerby's Creek, beginning at a stake in the Raleigh or Fayetteville Road running to a pine or Red Oak stump ... Contains one hundred acres more or less including all woody ways, waters and roads.
- M. A. Angier sold to H. J. Rigsbee, 1861 January 31 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, page 43, on September 21, 1885: a certain lot or parcel of land situated near Durham's Depot and bounded by Simon Terrell's line, containing about one eighth of an acre more or less. The store house family occupied by Durham and Angier occupies part of the lot.
- Simeon Ferrell sold to M. A. Angier, 1862 November 15 (Box 1)
  A tract or parcel of land bounded near to Durham's Station on the North Carolina railroad adjoining the lot of M. A. Angier Esq., containing one half acre more or less.
- M. A. Angier sold to Simeon Ferrell, 1868 (Box 1)
  A lot or parcel bounded near Durham's station on the North Carolina Rail Road adjoining the lots of M. A. Angier, A. M. Rigsbee and others ... by survey one half acre more or less.
- John V. Rigsbee sold to Atlas M. Rigsbee, 1869 February 12 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book M, page 144, on February 17, 1869: A house and lot in Durham adjoining the lands of M. A. Angier, A. M. Rigsbee, and others near Durham. Also another parcel of land, known as the Blacock tract, adjoining the lands of C.D. ..., David Vickers and others.
- George Laws sold to Atlas M. Rigsbee and Henry J. Rigsbee, 1869 February 15 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 45, page 380, on April 22, 1878: in the County of Orange, on the waters of New Hope adjoining the lands of C.P. Trice, David Nicken, known as the Blabcock tract, containing about twenty five acres. Also the other tract of Durham's Station on the N.C. Railroad adjoining the lands of John Strayhorn, John R. Green, and others containing about one hundred acres. Also one other small lot of land at Durham's Station containing one eighth acre which was bought of M. A. Angier and adjoins him, R.F. Morris and others.
- M. A. Angier and M. J. Angier sold to A. M. Rigsbee, 1869 April 20 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book M, pages 264-265 on June 2, 1869; and in deed book 38, page 264, undated: a lot of land lying in Village of Durham beginning at A. M. Rigsbee's corner on the line of my lot that I purchased of W. V. Pratt, along William Mangum's saw mill, along the lot formerly owned by Simeon Ferrell, along my lot known as the lot formerly owned by Shepherd Ferrell and Cheek, containing about 1/6 of an acre more less.
- A. M. Rigsbee and wife Rowena M. Rigsbee sold to Eugene Styron, 1869 May 17 (Box 1)
  A lot of land in the County of Orange, and Town of Durham adjoining and bounded by Thomas Rigsbee, M. A. Angier, A. M. Rigsbee. Also beginning in the center of Main or Pratt Street at Thomas Rigsbee's corner, containing 13/242 of an acre more or less. And also all the woods ways water and water courses.
- M. A. Angier and Mary J. Angier sold to A. M. Rigsbee, W. K. Styron, T. J. Rigsbee, 1871 September 9 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 40, page 425, undated: a certain lot of land in the corporate limits of the Town of Durham, beginning at the corner of A. M. Rigsbee's lot, to the well belonging to M. A. Angier and A. M. Rigsbee, to the Root of a Red Oak, to the line of W. and P. J. Magnum's Saw Mill Lot, to the Guard House Lot, along to T. J. Rigsbee's to W. H. Styron's corner, containing about one fourth acre more or less.
- Thomas J. Rigsbee and wife Nancy Rigsbee sold to Atlas M. Rigsbee, 1874 December 10 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, page 41, on September 21, 1885: the lot of land known as the Rigsbee, Styron and Rigsbee lot, and a certain lot on Main or Pratt Street adjoining W. K. Styron's lot commencing on Main or Pratt Street at W. K. Styron's, near the edge Mangum Street at Atlas M. Rigsbee's store.
- John V. Rigsbee sold to W. J. Mangum, 1875 January 12 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book R, page 178, on March 18, 1875: a certain portion of land received of W. K. J. Mangum on the south side of Main Street, east of the Drug Store lot of R. E. Styron by Main Street to R. E. Lyon's lot. And W. M. J. Mangum for the consideration of the portion of land received of John V. Rigsbee, enough of their land.
- M. A. Angier and wife Mary J. Angier sold to A. M. Rigsbee, 1875 July 18 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, pages 265-266, on November 21, 1885: beginning at a stake at Anderson Turner corner now A. M. Rigsbee corner to South Street, to Clay Street estimated to be one twentieth of an acre more or less.
- A. M. Rigsbee and wife Rowena M. Rigsbee sold to M. L. Carlton, 1875 December 11 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book R, page 194, on March 18, 1875: lot or parcel of land lying in the Town of Durham N.C. adjoining the lots of W. K. Styron, J. J. Rigsbee, A. M. Rigsbee, W. E. Styron to property belonging to M. L. Carlton.
- W. K. Styron and his wife Sallie Styron sold to A. M. Rigsbee, 1876 October 3 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 1, pages 16 and 17 registered on September 7, 1881: parcel begins at the corner of A. M. Rigsbee store house lot, north of the well belonging to M. A. Angier and A. M. Rigsbee running to a Red Oak, along W. and P. J. Mangum's Saw Mill lot, along the Guard House lot, to T. J. Rigsbee's line, to W. K. Styron's corner to A. M. Rigsbee's lot, containing about one fourth acre more of less.
- M. L. Carlton and wife B. V. Carlton sold to John V. Rigsbee, 1876 December 4 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, page 67, on September 21, 1885: a tract or lot of land in Orange County, State of North Carolina in Town of Durham, adjoining the lands of W. K. Styron Hunt and Wright and A. M. Rigsbee and others, along the lot formerly T. J. Rigsbee's, and A. M. Rigsbee and W. K. Styron's line on Main Street to the edge of Mangum Street, as by reference to the deed from A. M. Rigsbee to M. L. Carlton.
- W. K. Styron property by Thomas H. Hughes, sheriff, sold to W. T. Blackwell, 1879 January 27 (Box 1)
  A lot of land or parcel beginning in Center of Main or Pratt Street, to Thomas Rigsbee's corner, along M. A. Angier's end of his Pratt lot.
- John V. Rigsbee and Mary W. Rigsbee, his wife, sold to James A. Cheek, 1879 May 6 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 46, on page 68: adjoining the lands of A. M. Rigsbee and James T. Hunt beginning at the south east corner of A. M. Rigsbee's (Styron) store lot on Main Street, along James T. Hunt's line, along A. M. Rigsbee's line to A. M. Rigsbee's (Styron) store line.
- Malbourne A. Angier and Mary Jane Angier, his wife, sold to Atlas M. Rigsbee, 1880 January 9 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, on page 46, registered on September 21, 1885: beginning at the street edge of Mangum Street, at Main Street to Markham's corner, along Clay Street, more or less about twenty seven one hundreths of an acre.
- Malbourne A. Angier sold to the Town of Durham, 1880 June 25 (Box 1)
  "Prior to the 9th day of September 1871 and the said deed has been lost or mislaid by the officers of said Town." The property is the Guard House lot bounded by A. Angier, W. and J. J. Mangum, and T. J. Rigsbee, and A. Angier, being twenty feet square.
- Edward J. Parrish, Rosa B. Parrish, his wife, and James W. Blackwell sold to Atlas M. Rigsbee, 1880 September 10 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, pages 248-250, on November 20, 1885: beginning along Parrish and Blackwell's warehouse, along the old Mangum line, to T. J. Rigsbee's corner on Glenn's line, containing six hundredths of an acre more or less.
- T. J. Rigsbee sold to A. M. Rigsbee, 1880 October 15 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, page 40, on September 21, 1885: in the rear of Hunt's storehouse lot along Main Street to the shelter at Parrish and Blackwell's warehouse along to A. M. Rigsbee's line to T. J. Rigsbee's to the old Guard House.
- Town of Durham sold to A. M. Rigsbee, 1881 June 25 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, pages 237 and 237, on November 21, 1885: the small lot of land known as the Guard House lot, purchased by E. J. Parrish for A. M. Rigsbee, bounded by Clay Street, Church Street, Main Street, and Magnum Street, adjoining the lands of A. M. Rigsbee and T. J. Rigsbee, being twenty feet square more or less.
- James A. Cheek and his wife Rosa F. Cheek sold to William Maynor, 1884 May 14 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, on page 85: beginning at the corner of A. M. Rigsbee's store lot on Main Street, to James T. Hunt's line, to A. M. Rigsbee's line.
- William Maynor and Mary Ann Maynor, his wife, sold to A. M. Rigsbee, 1884 May 14 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 4, page 80, on September 24, 1885: adjoining the lands of James Y. Hunt and A. M. Rigsbee.
- Ella B. Markham agreed to an easement to allow A. M. Rigsbee use along a property, 1902 November 29 (Box 1)
  Registered in deed book 27, page 496, on December 3, 1902: alley on Parrish Street.
- Deeds envelope, undated (Box 1)